Grove Press Records
Grove Press Records
1948-1998
Grove Press.
600 linear ft.
Papers of the American publishing house founded by Barney Rosset. Collection contains a small amount of personal correspondence from owner Barney Rossett, but the majority consists of files relating to the company's production of books, Evergreen Review magazine, films and record albums. For any given title, this may include contracts, correspondence, legal records, photographs, publicity material, reviews, royalty statements, and production records. Notable authors represented in the collection include Emmanuelle Arsan, Alan Ayckbourn, Imamu Amiri Baraka (Leroi Jones), Samuel Beckett, Eric Berne, Paul Bowles, James Broughton, William S. Burroughs, Marguerite Duras, Wallace Fowlie, Robert Frank, Jean Genet, Allen Ginsberg, Maurice Girodias, Witold Gombrowicz, Juan Goytisolo, Nat Hentoff, André Hodeir, Eugène Ionesco, Jack Kerouac, D.H. Lawrence, Henry Miller, Pablo Neruda, Frank O'Hara, Charles Olson, Joe Orton, Harold Pinter, George Reavey, John Rechy, Kenneth Rexroth, Alain Robbe-Grillet, Michael Rumaker, Hubert Selby, Gilbert Sorrentino, Amos Tutuola, Parker Tyler, Tomi Ungerer, Alan Watts, and others. There are extensive legal records and clippings files relating to the censorship trials surrounding the American publication of D.H. Lawrence's Lady Chatterley's Lover and Henry Miller's Tropic of Cancer.
149514
Biographical History
Grove Press began as a small independent publisher in New York City's Greenwich Village in 1949. Within three decades, it grew into a multimillion-dollar publishing company recognized as one of the twentieth century's great avant-garde publishing houses.
When Barney Rosset purchased Grove Press in 1951 after its establishment by John Balcomb and Robert Phelps, it had published only a handful of books. Ten years into Rosset's tenure as publisher, Grove's catalog included over five hundred titles, and the publishing house continued its expansion. Looking beyond books, Grove operated a film distribution business, a book club, a theater, the Evergreen Review magazine, and eventually became a publicly traded company. For a time, Grove even experimented with publishing children's books.
One of Grove's most well-known accomplishments was in introducing American audiences to European avant-garde theater. From Alfred Jarry's late nineteenth-century experimental works The Ubu Plays to the absurdist plays of Samuel Beckett, Harold Pinter, Jean Genet, and Tom Stoppard, as well as the epic theater of Bertolt Brecht, Grove frequently sought to disseminate new drama in affordable paperback editions.
Rosset's interest in another artistic genre, film, led Grove Press to enter the film distribution business in 1966 when it purchased Cinema 16, the New York City film society founded by Amos and Marcia Vogel in 1947. The acquisition gave Grove access to many experimental films such as those by Maya Deren and Stan Brakhage. By the early 1970s, the Grove Press Film Division catalog included over four hundred domestic and international short and feature films, documentaries, experimental films, animations, and classic Charlie Chaplin and Georges Méliès films.
Rejecting mainstream notions of obscenity, morality, and decency, Grove also gained a reputation as a controversial publisher committed to fighting censorship as it published some of the most well-known banned books. Grove's success in publishing D.H. Lawrence's Lady Chatterley's Lover (1959) despite attempts to censor the work by the Post Office paved the way for Rosset to publish another contested work that was ultimately cleared by the courts, Henry Miller's Tropic of Cancer (1961) and defend the Evergreen Review. After winning several battles over the printed page, Grove built on these victories and successfully defended the screening of Vilgot Sjöman's Swedish film I Am Curious (Yellow).
Censorship was not the only social convention Grove had a role in shifting. The defining movements of the 1960s -- the antiwar, civil rights, black power, counterculture, and student movements in the United States, along with revolutions around the globe -- were debated, exposed, and discussed in Grove's publications as was the sexual revolution. Grove's books challenged prevailing attitudes about sex through dozens of erotic books, many by "anonymous" authors; introduced the layperson to new directions in psychology through Eric Berne's Games People Play; and gave voice to revolutionaries around the world, including Che Guevara and Malcolm X.
While Grove was successful in fighting censorship and obscenity laws and introducing groundbreaking works to American readers, internal conflicts and challenges such as efforts to unionize the staff and feminist criticisms confronted Grove in the 1970s, as well as the departures of long-time editors Dick Seaver and Fred Jordan. After many celebrated achievements and a peak in staff numbers and office size, Grove reorganized and downsized its operations. Ann Getty and British publisher George Weidenfeld purchased Grove Press in 1985 for a reported two million dollars. Rosset left in 1986 and continued to pursue publishing and an Internet-only version of Evergreen Review until his death in 2012. Grove continues to exist today as part of publisher Grove Atlantic.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The network of interrelationships between Grove and its authors was both dense and complex. Some authors whose books were published by Grove also wrote for Evergreen Review or were involved in their film projects. Occasionally Grove would ask one author to read another author's book and give their opinion, either formally or informally, or to write an introduction for it. Grove editors often built personal relationships with their authors. For all these reasons, material relating to one author or organization may be found in several places.
William Burroughs is a good example. Files relating to Burroughs' books are in boxes 169-178, but Burroughs also wrote prefaces or introductions to J.G. Ballard's Love and Napalm (Box 71) and Larry Sloman's Reefer Madness (Box 662). He corresponded with Grove authors Don Allen (Box 4) and Maurice Girodias (Box 297), and with Grove generally (Box 890). Grove asked him to review Justine: Philosophy in the Bedroom (Box 620) and he provided feedback on Alexander Trocchi's Cain's Book. John Rechy wrote a letter on his behalf (Box 584). þPieces by him appear in an issue of Leroi Jones' Floating Bear (Box 392) and in a dozen issues of Evergreen Review (4/11, 5/20, 6/22, 6/25, 7/29, 8/32, 8/34, 11/46, 12/52, 12/60, 13/67, and 15/94).
For this reason, the researcher is advised to search the entire finding aid for occurrences of the name(s) of interest. With most web browsers, CTRL-F will bring up a search box.
The Grove Press Records are divided into eight series.
Barney Rosset personal papers is a small group of materials related to the personal life of Grove Press publisher Barney Rosset. It contains correspondence, lecture notes, invitations and similar items.
The two Books series comprise the bulk of the collection. Books - Book files (by author) contains editorial and production records for books published by Grove Press, arranged alphabetically by author and within that by title. These materials reveal Grove's practices as a publisher and document the history behind Grove's books in addition to the personal relationships Grove staff members had with many of their authors, particularly Samuel Beckett. Anything generated or used in the process of publishing a book may be included, but the most common types of material are:
Contracts
Correspondence with authors, other publishers, literary agents, translators and internal memos
Copyright certificates and applications
Galleys and other proofs
Manuscripts and translations, with or without corrections
Photographs and illustrations used in books
Artwork and layout designs
Manufacturing estimates, invoices for typesetting and printing, and sample book jackets
Publicity materials generated by Grove (press releases, advertisements) as well as clippings of print media coverage (articles, reviews)
Rights and permissions forms and correspondence from those seeking permission to use the works
Royalty statements
The material in the collection pertaining to each book varies widely in both type of material and volume. For some titles, researchers can trace the book's history from initial contact with the author and contract negotiations through production and printing to newspaper clippings of book reviews following publication and publication of later editions. For other titles, extant materials are scarce. In some cases there is material for books that Grove considered (and may have had under contract) but did not end up publishing.
Books - Correspondence-subject files contains additional material related to Grove's publishing activities in general, including the company's network of literary agents and book scouts. There is correspondence with agents, booksellers, and publishers, book- and publishing-related organizations (American Book Publishers Council, Colorado Booksellers Association, Illinois Freedom to Read Committee, International Publishers Congress, etc.), as well as material on various topics of interest to the company (book rack displays, censorship, college adoptions of Grove titles, foreign translation rights, Polish and Yugoslav writers, etc.). There is also material related to Grove's children's books, and to special series and imprints such as Profile Books and Evergreen Pilot Books (a.k.a. Writers and Critics). Of particular interest are letters from readers or the general public that Grove deemed worthy of keeping (Compliments; Crank and derogatory letters; Humorous letters). There is also correspondence with some notable individuals, such as poets John Ashbery and Lawrence Ferlinghetti, authors Laurent de Brunhoff and Archibald Macleish, photographer Emil Cadoo, and book dealer Jeff Rund. Numerous folders of manuscript logs, reader's reports, and rejections give insight into the type of material Grove accepted and why.
The Business files series contains administrative, corporate, and legal records pertaining to Grove Press and its various business ventures including theatre ownership. The bulk of this series relates to Grove's finances, personnel, real estate, and sales, as well as legal issues (particularly obscenity cases), the company's stock, and its business partnership with Random House and Whirlwind Book Company. Day to day operations of the Grove office are documented in memos, phone message logs, and calendars kept by Barney Rosset.
The Evergreen Records series contains material related to Grove's short-lived foray into the recording business, including contracts, correspondence, and other material. The collection also contains a number of LPs (33-1/3 rpm phonodiscs) issued by Grove.
The Evergreen Review series documents the operation and production of Grove's literary magazine, the Evergreen Review. This series is divided into two subseries. The first subseries, By issue, contains material relating to all 98 issues of the magazine, including correspondence with contributing authors, layouts, advertising, and publicity. The second subseries, Correspondence-subject files, contains material related to the magazine generally. This includes organizations (Association of Literary Magazines of America, Globe Mail Agency, National Organization for Women, etc.), events (Australian seizure, Bread Loaf Writers Conference), individuals (Samuel Beckett, Paul Bowles, William Burroughs, Allen Ginsberg, John Lahr, Henryk Musialowicz, Tennessee Williams), and topics (complimentary subscriptions, complaints, index to issues #1-31, instructions for running Evergreen Review, legal issues, letters to the editor, publicity for the magazine in general, etc.). Also included here are manuscripts accepted but (apparently) never used, some by notable authors such as James Agee, Bertolt Brecht, Dianne di Prima, Eugene Ionesco, Octavio Paz, Larry Rivers, and Jose Yglesias. There is also, naturally, material relating to subscriptions including renewal lists and subscriber card files. A small amount of financial material completes this series.
The Films series documents Grove's role as a distributor of avant-garde and experimental short and feature length films. This series is divided into three subseries. Correspondence-subject files, contains material related to the magazine generally, including film companies, film festivals, film catalogs, etc. Of particular interest is a slide carousel with accompanying script labeled "Presentation to Volkswagen on behalf of Grove Press film distribution plan." The other two subseries, Feature films and Short films, contains material relating to Grove's feature-length productions and short films, respectively. Typical material includes contract, correspondence, film stills, lab invoices for printing, publicity, and royalty statements. For some films, there is information (mainly royalty statements) about distribution by the Cinema 16 Film Library which Grove purchased. The collection also includes more than fifty 16mm film prints of both feature-length and short films.
Publicity includes advertisements for Grove imprints (Black Cat, Evergreen Playscript, etc.), media coverage of the company and/or its productions, book exhibits, catalogs, files of clippings on censorship and obscenity and the impeachment of Justice William O. Douglas, various themed mailings such as "Survival Kit for Our Generation" and "Black Experience", order forms, and publicity photos of published books. Several scrapbooks spanning 1957 to 1963 contain press releases, advertisements, catalogs, order forms, photographs, book covers, and similar material, as well as one ("The Acid File") consisting entirely of copies of articles and clippings about LSD.
Other Formats Available
Selected items from the collection have been digitized, and are available via.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series are arranged alphabetically by series title. Book files (by author) are arranged alphabetically by author; all other series are arranged alphabetically by title or topic.
Related Material
For additional material related to Grove Press, see also the following:
Austryn Wainhouse Papers
Loren Glass Interviews Relating to Grove Press
Kenneth Deardoff Collection Relating to Grove Press
Prix Formentor Collection
, which contains materials about the Prix International and Prix Formentor literary prizes.
Creative Film Foundation Records
Barney Rosset's personal papers are housed at the Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, which also has a small
Grove Press Collection
.
Separated Material
Published editions of Grove Press books have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Publishing, printing and book arts; Radicalism; Allen, Donald Merriam, 1912-; Arsan, Emmanuelle.; Ayckbourn, Alan, 1939-; Baraka, Amiri, 1934-2014.; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989.; Berne, Eric, 1924-; Bowles, Paul, 1910-1999.; Broughton, James, 1913-1999.; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.; Duras, Marguerite.; Fowlie, Wallace, 1908-1998.; Frank, Robert.; Genet, Jean, 1910-1986.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Girodias, Maurice.; Gombrowicz, Witold.; Goytisolo, Juan.; Hentoff, Nat.; Hodeir, André, 1921-2011.; Ionesco, Eugène.; Jordan, Fred.; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.; Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930.; Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930 -- Censorship.; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980 Censorship.; Neruda, Pablo, 1904-1973.; O'Hara, Frank, 1926-1966.; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970.; Orton, Joe.; Pinter, Harold, 1930-2008.; Reavey, George, 1907-1976.; Rechy, John.; Rexroth, Kenneth, 1905-1982.; Robbe-Grillet, Alain, 1922-2008.; Rosset, Barney.; Rumaker, Michael, 1932-; Schmidt, Judith.; Seaver, Richard.; Selby, Hubert.; Sorrentino, Gilbert.; Tutuola, Amos.; Ungerer, Tomi, 1931-; Tyler, Parker.; Wainhouse, Austryn.; Watts, Alan, 1915-1973.; Grove Press. -- Archives.; Grove Press. -- Film Division.; Evergreen review.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Authors, French.; Authors and publishers.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics) -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Avant-garde cinema.; Beat generation -- Poetry.; Censorship -- United States -- Cases.; Censorship -- Law and legislation -- United States.; Obscenity (Law) -- United States.; Literature, Experimental.; Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; 16mm (photographic film size); Audiotapes.; Book reviews.; Books.; Catalogs (documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Film stills.; Financial statements.; Galley proofs.; Legal files.; Manuscripts for publication.; Motion pictures (visual works); Negatives (photographs); Phonograph records.; Photographs.; Publishers' catalogs.; Royalty statements.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs); Authors.; Editors.; Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
One folder of resumes are restricted until 2057. Three boxes of stock certificates w/SSNs are restricted until 2057. Redacted copies are available for use by researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Grove Press, 1967-1987.
Inventory
- Barney Rosset, personal
  - 203 W. Houston property, 1962-1963; 1969,; 1973 (Box 1078)
  - Agnini, Cristina (wife), 1981; undated (Box 1078)
  - Austin Cooper, 1967-1968; car purchase (Box 1078)
  - Better Government Association, 1981 (Box 1078)
  - Financial miscellany (Box 1078)
  - Francis W. Parker School, 1955-1956 (Box 1078)
  - Hampton Waters property, 1967 (Box 1078)
  - Hiss, Alger, 1966 (Box 1078)
  - House and car miscellany (Box 1078)
  - Interviews, radio and tv, 1964-1965; includes complete transcript of WNBC Open Mind episode, "Literature of License?" (Box 1078)
  - Invitations, 1964-1971; parties, speaking engagements, dinners, serve on board of directors, etc. (Box 1078)
  - Jefferson Market Courthouse, 1959-1961; efforts to save neighborhood landmark (Box 1078)
  - Kennedy, Robert F., 1965 (Box 1078)
  - Keys, Luise and Anthony, 1966 (Box 1078)
  - Lecture material, clippings, articles notes, etc. (Box 1078)
  - Lindsay, John, 1957; 1960,; 1965-1966,; 1969-1970,; 1973 (Box 1078)
  - Musialowicz, Henryk, 1964 (Box 1078)
  - New York University, 1967 (Box 1078)
  - Photographs
    - Barney and Frances Steloff (Oversize 31)
    - Barney in office at 64 University Place (Oversize 31)
    - Barney, unidentified (Oversize 31)
    - Japan, visit to Kenzaburo Oē, Mar 1966 (Oversize 31)
    - Unidentified sepia print, woman and boy (Box 1078)
  - Porter, Rusty Loane, 1972; long letter about experience of working at Grove (Box 1078)
  - Radcliffe College lecture, 1960-1961 (Box 1079)
  - Ranghuty, Sofia, 1955-1958 (Box 1079)
  - Remer, Phil and Sara, 1956 (Box 1079)
  - Rosset, Hannelore "Loly" (wife), 1966; 1974-1975 (Box 1079)
  - Rosset, M.E. (father) (Box 1079)
  - Seaver, Dick, 1963; 1966; majority are from Seaver to Rosset while Rosset was away traveling (Box 1079)
  - Speaking engagements, 1964-1969 (Box 1079)
  - Travel, miscellaneous (Box 1079)
  - Trinity College, Hartford, 1962; lecture notes (Box 1079)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1961-1962; "Berkeley paperback lecture"; includes essay, "The paperback in our contemporary culture" by Cyril O. Houle (Box 1079)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1962; "Popular Arts in American culture" lecture (Box 1079)
  - University of California, Berkeley, "Speech apptmts." (Box 1079)
  - University of California, Berkeley, "Speech material, misc." (Box 1079)
  - University of Pennsylvania (Box 1079)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, A-Z (Box 1079)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, unidentified (Box 1079)
- Books - Book files (by author)
  - Abbott, Bruce
    - Sign of the Scorpion
      - Contract, Evergreen Book Club, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Production, Artwork (Box 1)
      - Production, Camera copy, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Production, Manufacturing, 1969-1970; cloth (Box 1)
      - Production, Manufacturing, 1969-1970; 1981; Venus edition; Eveline by Anon. mentioned in reprint order quantities (Box 1)
      - Production, Setting copy (Box 1)
      - Project file, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Abdel-Malek, Anouar
    - Arab Political Thought
      - Project file, 1970; correspondence, contract (Box 1)
  - Abe, Kobo
    - Friends
      - Contract, 1968 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, Author, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, Translator, 1967-1969; Donald Keene (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
      - Invoices, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Photographs, Authors (Box 1)
      - Production, Manufacturing, 1969; 1976; includes photos, reprint (Box 1)
      - Production, Plate proofs (Box 2)
      - Publicity, 1969-1970; includes multiple copies of book jackets (Box 2)
      - Royalties, 1968-1970; includes Donald Keene (Box 2)
  - Abel, Lionel
    - Absalom
      - Rights and permissions, 1962; 1971 (Box 2)
  - Ableman, Paul
    - The Mouth
      - Correspondence, 1970; correspondence between Grove and The Running Man about publishing "The Mouth" by Ableman (Box 2)
    - Green Julia
      - Correspondence, 1966; 1968 (Box 2)
      - Contract, 1966 (Box 2)
      - Publicity, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
      - Royalties, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Abrahamsen, David
    - Who Are the Guilty?
      - Correspondence, Author, 1958-1959; 1961,; 1963 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1958; 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - Publicity, 1959; 1962; includes some in Italian (Box 2)
      - Royalties, 1958-1963 (Box 2)
  - Abt, Lawrence and Leopold Bellak
    - Projective Psychology
      - Contract, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, Author, 1958-1968; 1978,; 1983 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1959-1967; 1970,; undated (Box 2)
      - Photographs, Author (Box 2)
      - Production, Manufacturing, 1959 (Box 2)
      - Reader's Subscription, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
      - Royalties, 1959-1965 (Box 2)
      - Royalties, Editorial Paidos, 1965; 1967,; 1969 (Box 2)
      - Royalties, Longanesi and Co., 1960-1961; 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Actibom (coloring books)
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Acker, Kathy
    - Blood and Guts in High School
      - Production, Manuscript, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Adamov, Arthur
    - Ping Pong
      - Contract, copyright, 1967-1968; 1987; includes University Microfilms (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, Author, 1958-1959; 1961 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1956-1963; 1969,; undated; includes comments by Adamov on his plays; biographical sketch; except from speech given by Adamov at NYU shortly before play's premiere (Box 2)
      - Photographs, Author (Box 2)
      - Production, Camera copy, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Publicity, 1955; 1959 (Box 3)
      - Royalties, Editions Gallimard, 1958-1969 (Box 3)
      - Royalties, Richard Howard, 1959-1968 (Box 3)
    - Professor Taranne
      - Correspondence, 1968; 1970 (Box 3)
  - Adema, Marcel
    - Apollinaire
      - Correspondence, Author, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Photographs, Author (Box 3)
      - Production, Book cover (Box 3)
      - Publicity, Clippings, reviews, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
      - Royalties, copyright, contract, 1954-1959; 1969 (Box 3)
  - Adler, Alfred
    - Souvenirs Fresh and Rancid
      - Correspondence, Author, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Production, Setting copy, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Adler, Arthur
    - [unidentified manuscript, partial] (Box 3)
  - Adler, Kurt and Deutsch, Danica